so this is the uh Chanda Su Samaya
421 so once at
Sati Chanda approached the blessed one
paid homage to him sat down to one side
and said Venable sir what is the cause and
said Venable sir what is the cause and
reason why someone here is known as
rough and what is the cause and reason
why someone here is known as gentle so
I think he's he's asking if in this in
your Dum mind discipline what is who is
rough and who gentle who according to
the Buddha's understanding then okay yeah
Buddha's understanding then okay yeah
and so the Buddha replies here someone
has not abandoned lust because he has
not abandoned lust others irritate him
being irritated by others he manifests
his irritation he is known as
rough he has not abandoned hatred because he
he has not abandoned hatred because he
has not abandoned hatred others irritate
him being irritated by others he
manifests irritation he's known as rough
he has not abandoned distraction or AA
delusion because he has not abandoned
distraction others irritate him being
irritated by this he manifests
irritation he is known as rough this is
the cause and reason why one can be
known as
rough and then here someone has
abandoned lust because he has abandoned
lust others do not irritate him not
being irritated by others he does not
manifest irritation he is known as
gentle likewise with hatred and
distraction delusion this is the cause and the
delusion this is the cause and the
reason why one can be known as
gentle so I like the Su because
it's I know from
experience what is no know as rough and
gentle in the world is out outward
expression outward forms there is other
it says there was about the uh one monk
companions in the Holy life like softly
spoken always pleasing nice to be around
but of the wrong View and you should
avoid them
completely have anything to do with them
and then the alternative was like you
have roughly spoken not easy to be a
around difficult but of the right of you
and you should you should go and be with
them because that's what really matters
at the end of the
day now of course you can have
both or neither you have softly spoken
and the Right
View but the point is that the emphasis
should be on whether it's the right view
or
not that that kind of underlines the
behavior of this person and for that you
can't just use the external appearan as
a criteria
so yeah there's this yeah so that's the
issues that uh people want to use external
that uh people want to use external
things like clothing way of moving the
body exactly way of speak uniform
decorum which is again all all fine if
it's uh for like a I don't know like a
social harmony right yeah you don't go
and just start telling off a random
stranger you know but if somebody comes
to learn the D from you they're not a
stranger means they want to
learn so then if you come across like uh
not so pleasing in your expression and
if they refuse them to hear the DH
because of how you come across well
that's their great
loss because like you read the V stories
in the Su I mean the Buddha was far from
mildly mannered and softly spoken when
when monks did something wrong like the
names he called them the comparisons he
drawn between them and what they did it
was quite
horrific because of the weight of their
actions it was appropriate he wasn't
there to Pat you in the back he was
there to lead you out of some s
basically and you think that that can be
done with just like some skillful
communication and we all feel good no
even the world doesn't can't be solved
by that because again that's not the
root of the problem
like if you if your emphasis is on the
level of of how you communicate how you
come across not why you do so in other
words because of greed diversion or
delusion you'll never solve the problem
even if everybody never utters any bad
words again their intention remain
infected with with lust with aversion
with illusion which sooner or later
conflict will have to arise because
that's the root of
conflict so that's the problem like as I
said you
can whatever learn the manners and learn
how to speak properly and just it will
basically cause you less hassle in the
world people won't want attack you won't
won't be against you necessarily but
there is a limit to that but the problem
is like if you start
confusing uh learning a communication skill and
uh learning a communication skill and
how to express without offending anybody
and so on you start confusing that as
the development in the dharm that you're
completely misguided and people do
confuse that people of more more more
often than not they confuse uh
Psychotherapy and and and which a lot
revolves around learning the nonviolent
communication and learning all of this
they confuse that for the actual
practice of the Dharma people they've
been exposed to both I've seen that so
many times because yes you've actually
become better in worldly
terms but no amount of you
um
purifying your expression outward sh
cleaning your words up and and and
perfecting your outward shell no amount
of that would bring you any closer to
uprooting the G verion
delusion not an inch closer it will
probably take you further from it
because as I said now you're confusing a
random worldly practice for the practice
of the dhama and because of that you
won't look for what the actual practice
of the dhama is and
and so you can polish your outward shell
all you want but internally it's
absolutely filthy yeah still so your
speak theas are still there you are
still irritated and if you are still
irritated that's the root of the problem
that's the problem doesn't matter how
how soft the words you're using or how
you're walking slowly and you know doing
all the externally right things you're
coming from a place of irritation and
and would have said that in that uh I
don't remember the the reference but it
was basically when he said it was a
perfect harmony when the community is
perfectly harmonious not if they learn
how to talk to each other or if they
never use rough words no they're
perfectly harmonious if they all partake
in the same Right View so soopa is the
result of
Harmony the and see consequent like like
you could you could you could then
conclude very easily that okay so
without the Right View even if the
entire community it's just all smiles
and happiness and nice words that's not
Harmony that's basically circumstantial
agreeability yeah that will have to go
break apart at some point because the
root for the
um um that division still exists greed
ver delusion sensuality
desires it's the root of
suffering so if you're not free from
desires no amount of you padding your
expression and how you come across and
all of that will change
that as I said it will factually make
your life
easier and it's fine to do it for that
reason like you know if you keep going
around and whatever you say people just
constantly upset with you and harassing
you all the time as a result of it just
on a worldly basis because of how you
speak that harassment is a nuisance so
you just change your way you speak so
they'll stop harassing you so you can
then do your own
thing but when it comes to
dhama that like as I
said there is no room for compromise
there because people are already
entirely leaning away from DH with their
lifestyle with their desires with
everything else so now if you would not
want to say what the dhama is because
person who asked you a question might be
upset well you're actually that's that's
quite a demeritorious act to not say
what the dam is even if they get upset
yeah as there was a suit on that is even
if it upsets him well yeah yeah of
course there is a difference between
just going around in preaching and
trying to convert everybody to your
views and stuff then people have a right
to be upset even if if if the Buddha
himself is just teaching it the pur is
dumber but if a person comes to asks
comes to ask the question and and wants
to hear what you have to say and then
they get upset in kind of what you have
to
say because basically not and again they
will always they will always try and I
heard it many times they will always try
and say oh it's not what you said it's
how you said it and that just shows
which basically is not because I could
say it's not what you heard it's how you
heard it you could say the same it's
just blaming the other person now for it
but the fact is if you're honest with
yourself you would you would recognize
hold on yes I'm
upset and there is a there is like a
there is a pressure there is a there is
a there is like a desire to blame it on
how this person said it and how they
come across but is that really why I'm why am
across but is that really why I'm why am
I upset what if they said something that
I agree with and they said in the same
manner would I be
upset most likely not so the real reason
I'm upset is because I don't like what I
heard the message across the meaning
that I obviously got enough to upset me
I hate it I I I don't want to accept it
exactly so it's like so then all these
other Reflections will come in place so
why why am I affected by by by hearing
this why I don't like it why I resist it
why I why am I irritated by
it because it goes against my desires or
where my views are and it's like well
that in and of itself it's against the
practice of the
Dharma you know like that suta where
that somebody was criticizing the nuns
rightly or wrongly doesn't matter I
think it was wrongly actually even was
just criticizing the NS for wrong
reasons and this monk that was there was
their friend he got upset and the monk
was told off by the Buddha he's becoming
too intimate because he became too
intimate that he got upset when somebody
else was criticized regardless of
whether he was right of wrong
criticism so that's the am I getting
upset and he shouldn't get upset he
should get upet even if they get
tortured or or whatever well you
shouldn't get upset even if you get
tortured yeah let alone if it's not you
doesn't mean like you you ignore it or
you don't know what's happening or as I
said you don't know whether the
criticism is right or wrong no that's
all secondary it's more like am I moved
by this if so means I'm not abandoning
desire in regard to my own views and by
doing that by refusing to abandon it I'm
not practicing the D even if I'm
claiming to practice it yeah even if
you're Al looking like you're supporting
the dber so like issues with like I
support nuns and anyone who against nuns
uh that's wrong and you fight against it
because are you irritated yes so why why
is that because within you you're you're
maintaining hatred last you're not
supporting the dumb at all exactly so
all this outward work that you're doing
is actually not going to
benefit the dumb yeah it's not exactly
it's not going to it's just going to
revolve around worldly things it's going
to become a worldly thing even if that
was not necessarily your intentional
yeah um plan yeah so I mean yeah people
want you know you want to help uh you
want to not be uh hurtful to others you
want to be cruel and so on well you
don't have to take a course in
nonviolent communication you just have
to not hate them and not beit irritated
by them the thing that going to hurt
people restrain your
desires relinquish your your uh uh
Acquisitions and there will be no basis
for you being
obset or or the basis for you being
upset will will shrink depending on how
much you give up these things it's it's
as straightforward as
that and I think this this reminded me
of
um there's
uh there's these two words aesthetic and
athetic Aesthetics Aesthetics yeah aesthetic and
Aesthetics Aesthetics yeah aesthetic and
a I think that's the difference between
there's the Aesthetics the ones who give
up lust hatred and delusion on the level
that matters and then there's the
Aesthetics aesthetic
who just look like they've been giv up
they're giving it up on the level that
that it doesn't really matter yeah well
that that would kind of be all the all
the you know the ex the extreme
self-mortification practices they were
completely misguided in terms of the
Mind the mental intention and the
reasons behind which bu have said
they're as unbeneficial as as sensual
Pleasures are engaging with sensual
pleasure is so but yeah you could real
you could see that true you don't even
have to go to these extremes to fall
into that category all you need to do is
again are you are you reviewing or are
you prioritizing rather are you
prioritizing um your
um your
conviction that offers you security and
sense of pleasure and comfort or are you
willing to to question
it are you willing to to to Really
reflect upon and allow doubt to arise or
allow yourself to hear things you don't
want to hear and then if you dislike
them okay and or this is wrong if your
mind s is completely wrong it's like
okay it might be wrong but now I need to
understand why this which I just heard
that upsets me that goes against what I
think practice is that goes against what
I want practice to be why is it wrong is
it just because it goes against my
desires or because I factually
understand the contradiction in it and
and then even if you understand
contradiction in it um are you
relieved that that you found a
contradiction in it if so means you're
still invested with your
desires why were you threatened in the
first place if you were so sure where
the practice is you would not have been
threatened by something that was
presented as as as opposed to
it and so by not engaging in such
Reflections or by not allowing that to
arise you are on the level of of self
mortification they just sticks to their
conviction and then dismisses everything
else denal
yeah because that's again it boils down
to being free from those desires from
any desire from any need or finding
safety in the world in the ownership in
possessions in views and if if a person
is genuinely practicing dharm for those
reasons they won't be
by the manner of speaking or the
presentation because they are looking at
the bigger picture which is I'm about to
die I might not have much time left to
practice this rightly so please don't
waste my time with poetry and and sugar
coating your expression just tell me
what I need to do freedom from suffering
how do I get there how does that come
about you know straight one the straight
path yeah
and also of course as I said you use
common sense either way like it's not to
say that now you just have to tell the
hard bit truth to everyone in the face
even if they don't ask you that's just
dumb but if you know the person if
they're here to learn from you and
study and you're meaning words you are
doing them
diservice
it's not that's not compassionate no no
that's more like selfish for you because
you don't want
to come
across or basically you don't want to be
disliked let's put it that way oh if I
come across like this this person might
dislike me other person might dislike me
that's more important to me than
actually telling them what I already
know that can Benish F
them but then you don't really
know the D I suppose you might but
you're obviously maybe not as
established in it yeah just reemphasize
if you were to prioritize that over the
d means you need some development to do
yeah because it hasn't settled in yeah
if you if you're trying to cater your
external c yeah for those reasons means
your conceit still
overshadows any understanding that you might have
any understanding that you might have
because uprooting lust hatred that's
that that will sort that things will
work out you know that's just that's the
emphasis yeah but the key is like
again when you're asked because
sometimes you can equally put people off
by telling them what they don't want to
hear and they didn't ask you to hear it
no that's that's equally that can be
equally misguided yeah cuz sometimes
people get some understanding or some
sort of conviction and then they can't
resist the urge to go and preach to
everybody you know stand on the Town
Square and Shout to everybody because
this is the truth nobody asked
you even the Buddha himself who actually
I mean knew the clearest in all of its
fastest truth had to be asked to teach
he wouldn't just even even to the monks
on number of occasion Ananda would Rec
recogniz that was the under the skill to
recognize the right time to ask the Lord
for the teaching and then the word would
teach him